Guide to the Trout Mining Company Records 1933-1962
Montana Historical Society Archives
Trout Mining Company records
1933-1962
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-4774 mhslibrary@mt.gov
MC 316
Trout Mining Company.
.8 linear feet of shelf space
The Trout Mining Company produced manganese oxide for batteries. Records consist of scattered correspondence (1939-1951); payroll records (1956-1959), orders for equipment and supplies (1946-1953); production records, including a sample book (1958) for the Blaine Mine; reports; and miscellany, including field survey books (1936-1938).
The Trout Mine was first developed in 1870 by the Cole Saunders Gold and Silver Mining Company. The company's manager James Patten later formed his own company the Patten Mining Company and operated the mine in the early 1900s. During World War I, the Western Ore and Mining Company produced manganese from the mine. The Trout Mining Company was incorporated under Illinois law in 1922. It was re-incorported under New Jersey law in October 1924 and operated the mine until October 1936. In September 1936 the American Machine and Metals Manufacturing Corporation merged with Trout to form American Machine and Metals Inc. The Trout Mine became the Trout Division of the new company. The new company was headed by P.G. Mumford, while the Trout Division was managed by Charles A. Hyder. In 1947 and again in 1950 the Trout mill burned. In January 1958 a new Trout Mining Company was incorporated to take over the operation of the mine. It became inactive in 1963, though the charter did not expire until 1993.
Records consist of scattered correspondence (1939-1951); payroll records (1956-1959), orders for equipment and supplies (1946-1953); production records, including a hauling record (1962) and a sample book (1958) for the Blaine Mine; reports, including a report (1962) by the U. S. Bureau of Mines on the health and safety at the Algonquin Mine and Trout Mill; and miscellany, including field survey books (1936-1938).
by series
available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
American Machine and Metals, Inc. Trout Mining Division.
Manganese mines and mining--Montana--Granite County
Mines and mineral resources--Montana--Granite County
Granite County (Mont.)--industries
Philipsburg (Mont.)--industries
Montana
Business, Industry, and Labor
Mines and Mineral Resources
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- General Correspondence
  - F-G (correspondents include Lockwood W. Ferris, Bonneville Ltd; L. D. Frink; Galigher Company), 1939-1951 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
- Employment Records
  - Contract negotiations with International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers (IUMMSW) local and notice of cessation of work, 1960-1963 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Group health insurance with Montana Physicians Service (includes names of subscribers), 1960-1962 (Box-folder 1 / 2A)
  - Time books, 1956-1960 (Box-folder 1 / 3-5)
- Financial Records
  - Orders for equipment and supplies: A-W, 1946-1953 (Box-folder 1 / 6-8)
- Production Records
  - Hauling record, 1962 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - Sample book (assays): Blaine Mine, 1958 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
  - Miscellaneous (includes metallurgy of lessees' ore Algonquin Mine, Treetop Mine work, ore reserves of Algonquin, True Fissure, and Scratchall Mines), 1962, 1964, undated (Box-folder 2 / 3)
- Reports
  - Review of operations and financial condition, 1959 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - U. S. Bureau of Mines report on health and safety at Algonquin Mine and Trout Mill, 1962 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
- Miscellany
  - American Machine and Metals Company list of records sent to Philipsburg, 1960 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - Field survey books (includes geology notes, mine sketches, survey notes, assays, production figures, etc.), 1933-1938 (Box-folder 2 / 7-9)
  - Machinery recommended for 200 ton plant, 1930 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
- Transfers to Other Programs
  - Geology map transferred to Library Map Collection, 1962 (Box-folder 2 / 11)